so we have seen in the previous quiz
that the one bit predictor cannot really
predict well the pattern n NT that
repeats we will see that a 2bit history
will be successfully predicting this
pattern how does a two-bit history
predictor work same as before we take
the PC and we index into the branch
history table from which we get an entry
now however the entry we get has five
pieces it has two bits of History so
these are the last two outcomes of this
branch and then we have four times a two
bit counter one for each possible
history so with two bits we will index
into this array of counters and use the
appropriate counter for the given
history so as you can see the overall
cost of this predictor now is two bits
of History plus 4 * 2 so it ends up
costing us 10 bits per Branch instead of
going through a lengthy example of how
this works when we try to predict this
pattern let's try to figure it out the
sequence of outcomes is n n t n and T
Etc when we are seeing the outcome of T
and trying to predict it that is we're
trying to predict what will become T our
2bit history will be 0 0 it's saying
that the last two outcomes we have seen
have been both not taken this history
will make us use this counter here so
that counter which we will call counter
number zero will be counting up when
we're trying to predict this particular
outcome our history will be 01 we will
be using counter number one and we will
decrement it because we seeing a non-t
taken decision when we're trying to
predict this the history will be 1 Z
this
corresponds to counter number two which
will also be decremented for this now we
will again use the history of 0 0
because the last two outcomes have been
not taken this means that the counter
number zero because of this taken
decision will be incremented and so on
as you can see counter zero always
counts up so very soon it will start
predicting taken which means every time
we see a history of 0 0 we will start
predicting strong taken counter one
keeps counting down so very very soon
after seeing a history of 01 we will
predict strong not taken and similarly
counter two is always counting down so
very soon we will start predicting not
taken when we see a history of one Zer
as you can see what's now going to
happen is pretty much this counter zero
here will start to predict strong taken
counter one will start to predict strong
not taken and counter two is going to
predict strong not taken counter number
three which is is the last counter we
have actually never gets used because we
never see a history of 1 one that would
mean that we have seen a taken followed
by a taken which doesn't happen in this
particular pattern so as you can see
this predictor starts being a perfect
predictor after a while after these
counters have been appropriately
modified depending on their starting
state so unlike a single bit history
predictor a two- bit history can predict
this pattern accurately